Guide to the Susan Otis Thompson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Susan Otis Thompson Papers,
1965-1992
[Bulk Dates: 1970-1980]
Thompson, Susan Otis
1.05 linear ft. (2.5 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1561
6915494
The papers consist primarily of correspondence and documentation related to her professional activities as a professor, a librarian, and a scholar of early print and book history.
Biographical Note
Susan Otis Thompson was a teacher, author, editor, lecturer, and researcher, best known for her scholarship on William Caxton and the history of the book.
Thompson enrolled at Columbia University's School of Library Service, where she earned both her M.S. (1963) and D.L.S. (1972). She began as an intern in the University Libraries Reference Department. She gradually took on teaching duties and rose through the academic ranks, becoming a teaching assistant, lecturer, preceptor, assistant professor, and finally an associate professor in 1978. Starting in 1966 she began teaching a course on the History of the Book that she would continue to teach until the school's closing in 1992. She also contributed, alongside Terry Belanger, to the establishment of Columbia's Master's program concentration in Rare Books, Manuscripts, and Special Collections, the first of its kind in the U.S. (1973). This program would later become the independent Rare Book School, now located at the University of Virginia.
With research interests in rare books and manuscripts, book and printing history, library history, rare book librarianship, book design, typography, graphic arts, and the Arts and Crafts movement, Thompson published American Book Design and William Morris in 1977 (Bowker), which was reprinted in 1996 by Oak Knoll Press and the British Library. As both a writer and editor, she contributed to numerous publications, including The Arts and Crafts Movement in America 1876-1916 (1994), The Heritage of the Graphic Arts Lecture Series: A Complete Listing (1994), and William Caxton: An American Contribution to the Quincentenary Celebration (1976), a chapbook published by the Typophiles printed for the Caxton International Congress (1976), which marked the 500th anniversary of the introduction of printing into England. Thompson also spoke around the country at seminars, conferences, and panel discussions.
Thompson was an active member of numerous book history societies, including the Typophiles, the William Morris Society, and the Corrodentia Society, and in 1977 she became one of the first women allowed to join the Grolier Club. She was also a founding member of the American Printing History Association (APHA) (1974) and served as the editor of APHA's semiannual journal Printing History from 1979-1983.
Thompson died of breast cancer in 2008.
Scope and Content
Thompson's papers consist primarily of correspondence, clippings, and printed materials related to her professional activities as a librarian, teacher, and scholar of book history.
The strength of the papers lies in their documentation of topics pertaining to the history of libraries, books, and library science in the late twentieth century. A scholar in early book history and book design, her papers contain documentation and artifacts from Thompson's research, as well as correspondence with Leo Wyatt, L. Carrington Goodrich, and Herbert Kleist. Thompson's papers also document the activities of the now-defunct School of Library Service at Columbia University, including the establishment of a rare books librarianship concentration that would later become the Rare Book School, and the activities of numerous library- and book history-related organizations, most notably the formative years of the American Printing History Association (APHA). The papers also include manuscript drafts, speeches, and correspondence related to Thompson's research, publications, and speaking engagements.
Of additional note is a manuscript on the state of libraries in Nigeria and Kenya (1965). A small set of black-and-white photographs are included with the report.
The collection contains a small amount of information describing the Grolier Club's contribution to the establishment of the Columbia University rare books progam, but little else of note. Papers related to the William Morris Society are too few to be considered significant.
The material type of the collection is mixed.
Arrangement
This collection has been left in its original physical order but has been intellectually arranged into six series. Although a few papers have been assigned as general correspondence, it should be noted that all six series contain correspondence specific to their respective topics.
Series I. Columbia University School of Library Service, 1972-1987, Undated
Series II. Correspondence -- General, 1969-1992
Series III: Professional Development, 1976-1977, 1980, 1986, 1991-1993
Series IV. Publications, 1965-1986
Series V. Service and Committees, 1971-1979, 1982
Series VI. Speaking Engagements, 1971-1980
Subjects
American Library Association; American Printing History Association; American Printing History Association--Conference; Association of College and Reference Libraries; Association of College and Reference Libraries--Rare Books and Manuscripts Section--Preconference; Columbia University.--School of Library Service; Columbia University.--School of Library Service--History; Grolier Club; National Conservation Advisory Council (U.S.); New York Library Association; New York Metropolitan Reference and Research Library Agency; Rare Book School; Trumbull College (Yale University); Adams, Rrandolph Greenfield, 1892-1951; Beilenson, Edna, 1909-1981; Bellanger, Terry; Caxton, William, ca. 1422-1491 or 2; Dunlap, Joseph R. (Joseph Riggs), 1913-; Goodrich, L. Carrington (Luther Carrington), 1894-; Kleist, Herbert, 1902-1986; Leslie, Robert L., 1885-1987; Morris, William, 1834-1896; Shoemaker, Richard H.; Thompson, Susan Otis; Wyatt, Leo, 1909-1981; Arts and crafts movement; Book design--History; Book design--United States--History; Graphic Arts--History; History of the book; Librarianship and information studies; Libraries--History; Libraries--Kenya; Libraries--Nigeria; Printing--History; Typography; Rare books
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Susan Otis Thompson Gift 1996
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I. Columbia University School of Library Service, 1972-1987, Undated
  This series consists of correspondence, newsletters, committee minutes, notes, and event documentation related to the activities and operations of the Columbia University School of Library Service. The series includes a selection of issues of Library Service News, offering insight into the regular activities of the department, faculty, and alumni, as well notes, place cards, and photographic slides from early printing and private press exhibits held in the library. This series also contains documentation of the establishment of a program concentration in Rare Books, Manuscripts, and Special Collections, including an unsigned letter draft presumably written by Terry Belanger in which he details the need for the program and provides a brief synopsis on the Grolier Club's association with it, and on the 1987 conference on Libraries and Scholarly Communication in the United States sponsored jointly by Columbia University and the Center for the Book in the Library of Congress.
  - Committee on Goals and Objectives, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Instruction, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Research and Academic Librarianship, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Conference on Libraries and Scholarly Communication (co-sponsored by Library of Congress), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee, 1984-1985, 1987-1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Library Exhibits, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3 to 4)
  - Library Service News, 1972-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rare Books and Special Collections Concentration, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statutory Faculty, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series II. Correspondence -- General, 1969-1992
  This series contains correspondence and related materials that do not explicitly relate to Columbia University's School of Library Service or Thompson's professional development activities, publications, service activities, or speaking engagements. (Correspondence related to such categories are housed in their respective series.) This series contains correspondence with Leo Wyatt on the topic of calligraphy (1977-1981), L. Carrington Goodrich on the disputed timeline of Oriental printing (1969-1992), and Herbert Kleist on book bindings (1974-1975).
  - Correspondence with L. Carrington Goodrich (on Oriental printing), 1969-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Leo Wyatt (on calligraphy), 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Herbert Kleist on bookbindings, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series III. Professional Development, 1976-1977, 1980, 1986, 1991-1993
  This series contains documentation of seminars and conferences that Thompson attended as an attendee rather than a speaker. Invitations, schedules, and lists of registrants are included.
  - American Library Association (ALA) Centennial Library History Seminar, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - American Printing History Association (APHA) -- Conferences, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Association of College and Research Libraries (ACRL) -- Rare Books and Manuscripts Section Preconferences, 1977, 1980, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series IV. Publications and Manuscripts, 1965-1986
  This series contains correspondence, manuscripts, clippings, and notes related to articles and books written by, edited by, and compiled by Thompson, including Caxton: An American Contribution to the Quincentenary Celebration (1976) and American Book Design and William Morris (1977). This series also contains a manuscript report on the state of libraries in Nigeria and Kenya (1965) with a small set of accompanying black-and-white photographs.
  - American Book Design and William Morris, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Printing History Association (APHA) -- First Annual Conference, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Caxton: An American Contribution to the Quincentenary Celebration, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dictionary of American Biography Article on Randolph. G. Adams, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dictionary of American Library Biography Article on Richard Shoemaker, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Libraries in Nigeria and Kenya (manuscript), 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Reader on Rare Book Librarianship, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Robert L. Leslie Festschrift, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series V. Service and Committees, 1971-1979, 1982
  This series includes correspondence, minutes, and related materials documenting the committees and advisory councils on which Thompson served. (Service specific to the Columbia University School of Library Service is located in Series I.) This series contains documentation from the first annual conference of the American Printing History Association (1976), which is also co-located in Series IV and VI.
  - American Library Association (ALA) Library History Round Table, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - American Printing History Association (APHA)
    - First Annual Conference, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5 to 6)
    - National Officers Election, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Committee on Teaching the History of the Book, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Association of College and Research Libraries (ACRL)
    - Rare Books and Manuscripts Section -- Committee to Study Special Education for Training Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Librarians, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Rare Books and Manuscripts Section -- Continuing Education Committee, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Corrodentia Society, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Heritage of the Graphic Arts, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Conservation Advisory Council, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series VI. Speaking Engagements, 1971-1980
  This series contains correspondence, documentation, notes, and text of speeches delivered by Thompson at panel, conference, and seminar appearances.
  - Corrodentia Society, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New York Metropolitan Reference and Research Library Agency (METRO) Conservation Seminar, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typophiles Christmas Luncheon for Joseph Dunlap, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - American Printing History Association (APHA) -- First Annual Conference, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Society of Printers (Boston), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - University of Alabama -- Symposium on the Book Arts, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Printing History Association (APHA) -- New York Chapter, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cooper-Hewitt Museum -- Book Arts Program, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - New York Library Association Conference Panel on Special Collections, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Trumbull College -- Dedication of Sherman Foster Johnson Press, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rochester Institute of Technology -- Goudy Award for Edna Beilenson, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)